<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: methods | Chris's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://cbilson.github.io//blog/categories/methods/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cbilson.github.io//"/>
  <updated>2013-08-19T20:19:21-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://cbilson.github.io//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Bilson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[cbilson@pobox.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Research Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://cbilson.github.io//blog/2013-06-12-research-day.html"/>
    <updated>2013-06-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://cbilson.github.io//blog/research-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-1">Abstract</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1">
<p>
"Research Day" is a time when software developers stop working on
features and spend time trying to learn things that will help improve
their work in the future. This can help teams learn, innovate, and
break into system-thinking. In this post I discuss some things
I've found that work and some things that don't.
</p>

<p>
<!-- more -->
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-2">Overview</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2">
<p>
The idea of having a "Research Day," "<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/21/jobs/21pre.html?_r%3D0">20% Time</a>," "<a href="http://www.fastcodesign.com/1663137/how-3m-gave-everyone-days-off-and-created-an-innovation-dynamo">15% Time</a>," or other
mechanisms for developers to break away from their day to day tasks
and change modes of thinking is nothing new. Google, for example,
famously uses 20% time both as a <a href="http://computer.howstuffworks.com/googleplex3.htm">benefit with which to attract talent</a>
and as a way to <a href="http://www.eweek.com/c/a/IT-Infrastructure/Top-20-Percent-Projects-at-Google/">get innovative new ideas out of their people</a>.
</p>

<p>
I've personally had some experience with things like this and came to
the conclusion that, with a little discipline and structure, Research
Day can be adapted to most businesses and become essential to a highly
functioning team.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-3">Things That Don't Work</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3">
<p>
Here are some of the problems/myths I have found that detract from
the value of Research Day.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-sec-3-1" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-3-1">You Are Not Google</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-3-1">
<p>
&#x2026;unless you actually <span class="underline">are</span> google, in which case disregard that.
</p>

<p>
To the rest of you: observe Google's mission statement: <a href="http://investor.google.com/corporate/faq.html#toc-mission">"Organize
the World's Information</a>."  In the "Information Age" it's hard to
imagine anything productive you could do with a computer that
wouldn't further that goal.
</p>

<p>
Chances are your company's mission statement is narrower than
that. You should probably focus on things that are actually in line
with <b>your</b> company's mission. If you are not quite sure how to
connect the thing you want to do to your company's mission in <a href="http://www.mindtools.com/pages/article/newTMC_5W.htm">5 Whys</a>,
then it's probably not a great work research day project. By all
means, still research it, just on your own time.
</p>

<p>
So if you were planning on writing the next great rails view engine
and you work in a place that does nothing but .NET WPF applications,
you might want to choose something else to research. It's important to
be able to demonstrate the value of the work you are doing all the
time, but especially when what you are doing might not appear overtly
productive to other people you work with.
</p>

<p>
Research stuff that matters.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-3-2" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-3-2">If You Don't Produce Anything, It's Not Research</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-3-2">
<p>
Research is a product - some*thing* produced. If you don't produce
anything, then, by definition, it's not research.
</p>

<p>
I've personally had days when I did "Research Day" and had no output -
not even an e-mail explaining what I'd found to my teammates. If
pressed, my excuse might have been something like, "well&#x2026;I realized
that this «whatever» isn't a great fit for what we are doing&#x2026;" I
will never get those days back. Just writing down your findings is the
difference between a productive but negative research day and a
complete waste of time and money. Why wasn't «whatever» a bad fit? Is
whatever made «whatever» a bad fit still valid? How will we know if we
don't produce something that says what basis we made these
judgments on.
</p>

<p>
On my last team we kind of settled on the idea of writing up our
findings in a Research-Paper-like format (like I am trying to do here,
for this blog post.) I think on that team, we generally valued the
formal, academic feeling that gave and we were big into arguing about
stuff, so trying to clearly state the case for what you concluded from
your research was important to us.
</p>

<p>
That said, I wouldn't claim that we <span class="underline">always</span> wrote up the results of
our research. It's not always appropriate for every topic and
sometimes just having code that clearly shows something is
better.
</p>

<p>
But generally, I'd say you need to have some written language results
for it to be research day - even an email summary or a README to go
along with any code you wrote. You are saving the code you wrote, right?
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-3-3" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-3-3">Don't Work Production Code Into Research</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-3-3">
<p>
This is a tough one. It's easy to fall into thinking that if you do
your research work in your production code it will be more likely to
lead to something valuable that you can use right away when you go
back to &not; Research day.
</p>

<p>
I don't think that's research. That's hacking, working, spiking
(not really, but that's what some people think&#x2026;topic for another
time), or something, but it's not research. You aren't stepping
outside your day-to-day work. You're not getting a new
perspective. You're not considering a subject in isolation from all
the stuff you already have. It's too easy to confuse a systemic
problem in your day-to-day work for a factor in the thing you are
trying to research.
</p>

<p>
For example, let's say you want to research how to compile <a href="http://lesscss.org/">less</a> to
CSS in an ASP.NET MVC application. There are a lot of options, or
you could build something yourself. You should probably write some
sample code and write up some conclusion with an argument for and
against each of the various choices. Sounds like a busy day.
</p>

<p>
If you start in your production code, you might spend 5 minutes
getting all your pages to use a new URL for their CSS and then turn
around and spend (read: waste) another 55 minutes figuring out why the
login page has some weird CSS quirk that turns out to be a bug that
you write a card about (10 more minutes.)
</p>

<p>
Say that only happens with one of the less to CSS engines you look
at. Would you incorporate this into your results? Is it a problem
with the less to CSS component? Even if you were careful, would it
be easy to accidentally incorporate bias against the less to CSS
component in your conclusion? Is it the thing you are trying to
evaluate that is wrong, or the system you are evaluating it in?
Also, remember, you just wasted 75 minutes you could have used more
productively exploring all the options or the other choices of less
to CSS engine.
</p>

<p>
Better to start with a simple example project that just demonstrates
the thing you are researching.
</p>

<p>
Another problem you might run into is that the research becomes
stale - something in the production code changed in the year since you
did the research and now it no longer compiles, or no one can remember
how we used to do something that the code you wrote is doing - we
can't tell if it's an important part of the research or just
noise. Research code that has too much production code in it is more
like a branch than clean, reproducible research, and has all the
maintenance burden of maintaining a branch.
</p>

<p>
If you write code as part of your research, I would encourage you to
start with a completely new, clean project, re-using as little
production code as possible (like ideally: NONE), and definitely not
polluting your production code with research.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-3-4" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-3-4">Don't Research if You Don't Have a Good Topic</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-3-4">
<p>
On my last team, we didn't do Research Day every week - not even
close. I think we did a good job of being pragmatic and only using
the time when we had legitimate things to research. I think the real
trick is having an abstract. If you can say something compelling
about what you want to research and what kind of results you hope to
see in a short, pithy abstract, I think you're onto something.
</p>

<p>
Some teams use research as a synonym for slack. I think this works
in the sense of "important but not urgent," but I find that a lot
of people don't really <span class="underline">get</span> slack and think of it as waste or goof
off time. If you are sure your team is using a definition like
<a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Blog/Slack%2520and%2520Scheduling%2520in%2520XP.html">this</a>, I think it's ok.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-4">What Does Work</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4">
<p>
Here are some things I've seen that worked:
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-sec-4-1" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-4-1">Have One Repository For All Your Research</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-4-1">
<p>
It's a lot easier to find research if it's all in one place. On one
team I was on, we tried using different git repos for each research
project and we found that made it hard to find things
sometimes. Better to have it all in one repo you can grep through
that a bunch of repos to clone and look through.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-4-2" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-4-2">Make Research Day All-Day</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-4-2">
<p>
When I first started on my last team, we were only doing research day
for half the day. We had a team lunch and I believe the original idea
was that you would share the results of your research with your
teammates over lunch.
</p>

<p>
At some point we were able to show that Research Day was a benefit to
the business and we got permission to extend Research Day to a full
day.
</p>

<p>
I found that half-day research was really superficial. I couldn't
afford take the time to really try anything more than reading
about something and maybe trying a couple of really simple
experiments, and then only if I was already semi-familiar with the
topic I was researching beforehand.
</p>

<p>
When we switched to full-day, I was able to go a lot deeper and be
more effective.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-4-3" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-4-3">Do Research Day on Friday</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-4-3">
<p>
It's the end of the week and you are ready for something different.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-4-4" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-4-4">Do Research Day on not-Friday</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-4-4">
<p>
You've just spent 4 days wallowing in your problems and they won't be
that easy to forget.
</p>

<p>
Plus Friday's tend to run a little short, which contributes to the
feeling that research day is goof-off time.
</p>

<p>
Come Monday, is anyone going to remember what you said you were going to
research and hold you accountable for not producing anything?
</p>

<p>
I think I prefer Monday Research Day, but Friday would be my
second choice. I am not sure why, but Research Day in the middle
of the week sounds like it would break your flow too much. Maybe
that would be a good thing? I don't know.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-4-5" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-4-5">Outline as You Go</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-4-5">
<p>
Getting back to the format of the research output, as I mentioned I
am partial to research paper style. To do this, I start by writing an
abstract, then an outline. I make a go/no-go decision after
this. Would I want to read this if I was one of my teammates? Would I
want to pay for this if I was a shareholder in my company? Would a
customer pay for it?
</p>

<p>
As I go, I fill in the outline. I try not to write too much - just
some hooks to fill in later. I end up deleting a lot, so writing too
much ahead of time is just typing practice, not research.
</p>

<p>
In the past, when I've waited until the end of the day to write stuff
up, it doesn't turn out well. I am pressed for time. Usually you end
up working on code samples or finding new things right up till it's
time to leave, so the final output is rushed and unplanned. Much
better to have a plan, find out as much as possible about what you
set out to find out about, and have something to show for it in the
end.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-4-6" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-4-6">Talk to Your Teammates Before and After</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-4-6">
<p>
This is akin to presenting a paper at a conference: your teammates
can ask questions, learn, and we can all get an idea of what was
missed in the research (maybe giving us ideas for future research.
</p>

<p>
Personally, nothing beats going out for beers on Friday after a
Research Day and talking to your teammates about what you found -
maybe not formal, but you get a different level of engagement that
way. Every team is different - some teams actually don't drink beer!
In those cases, adaptations can be made to accommodate - go out for
coffee maybe?
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-5" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-5">Conclusion</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-5">
<p>
At the end of the day, Research Days are a way for a team to
learn. There are other ways of course, but they often lack the rigor
and discipline you can get from Research Day.
</p>

<p>
Using knowledge the team gets from research as opposed to ad-hoc blog
reading, finding answers on stack overflow, or a lot of other ways
developers typically learn gives me the same feeling as using
production code that has been tested and well designed vs. something
someone found in a gist some evening while being late for dinner.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-6" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-6">Further Research</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-6">
<p>
You can find more ideas for organizing research days here:
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li><a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/slack.html">James Shore on Slack</a>
</li>
<li><a href="http://www.fastcodesign.com/1663137/how-3m-gave-everyone-days-off-and-created-an-innovation-dynamo">How 3M Gave Everyone Days Off and Created an Innovation Dynamo</a>
</li>
<li><a href="http://www.assemblymag.com/articles/87753-lean-manufacturing-the-abcs-of-a3-reports">The ABCs of A3</a> - maybe an alternative to research-paper-style
presentation of findings?
</li>
<li><a href="http://a3thinking.com/whatis.html">More A3 Stuff</a>
</li>
<li><a href="http://spectrum.ieee.org/podcast/at-work/tech-careers/telecommuting-and-yahoos-desperate-need-for-innovation">IEEE Podcast Interview with Steven Cherry</a> - ostensibly about
telecommuting, but he also talks a about innovation
</li>
<li><a href="http://www.thetakeaway.org/2013/feb/27/pros-and-cons-telecommuting/">The Pros and Cons of Telecommuting</a> - More Steven Cherry stuff. I
find this guy kind of interesting.
</li>
<li><a href="http://www.ere.net/2013/02/26/how-yahoos-decision-to-stop-telecommuting-will-increase-innovation/">How Yahoo's Decision to Stop Telecommuting Will Increase
Innovation</a> - OK, last Steven Cherry link&#x2026;
</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-sec-6-1" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-6-1">Writing Papers</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-6-1">
<p>
Being mostly self-educated, I had <b>read</b> a lot of papers but never
written any until I started using them in Research Day. If you are
like me, you might find the following links useful:
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li><a href="http://www.wikihow.com/Write-a-Research-Paper">How to Write a Research Paper</a>
</li>
<li><a href="http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/simonpj/papers/giving-a-talk/writing-a-paper-slides.pdf">How to Write a Great Research Paper</a> - slides from a talk by
Simon Peyton Jones, one of my nerd heros.

<p>
Additionally, I get a lot of bang-for-the-buck out of writing in
emacs, with org-mode. It has a lot of features to make it easy to
write good looking documents, with colorized code blocks (that you can
even execute inside the document!), latex, and other fanciness. It's
also great at outlining and building up the structure of a document
and managing tasks related to your research inside the document. I
could go on, but won't. If you're interested, check out some of these
links:
</p>
</li>

<li><a href="http://tincman.wordpress.com/2011/01/04/research-paper-management-with-emacs-org-mode-and-reftex/">Research Paper Management with Emacs, org-mode and RefTeX</a>
</li>
<li><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/10864824/organizing-my-papers-in-org-mode">Organizing my papers in org-mode</a>
</li>
<li><a href="http://orgmode.org/worg/org-contrib/babel/uses.html">Source Code Blocks: Uses</a>
</li>
<li><a href="http://web.warwick.ac.uk/statsdept/user2011/TalkSlides/Contributed/16Aug_1115_FocusI_4-ReportingWorkflows_3-Leha.pdf">The Emacs Org-mode - Reproducible Research and Beyond</a>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/thinkagain">Think Again - How to Reason and Argue</a> - I really enjoyed this
Coursera course and found it helped me improve my ability to
make a point in my research.
</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-6-2" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-6-2">Numbers</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-6-2">
<p>
While I remain convinced Research Day is an important practice, I've
never actually measured this. It would be really interested to hear
from anyone that has any work that shows measurable value in Research
Day, outside of companies like Google and examples like the well
worn post it example.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-6-3" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-6-3">Ad-Hoc Research Day</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-6-3">
<p>
Another idea I am interested in is making Research Day an ad-hoc
thing. How would you manage this and make sure it didn't get out of
control? Would it just be one of those "trust us" kind of things? I
think some teams could pull this off.
</p>

<p>
This seems like it could be one of those lean things where
efficiencies are realized by doing the work just in time, right
before it's needed. Since research kind of spoil over time, this
might be a good technique to try.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
